Finding Aid for A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning (University of Michigan) publications, 1876-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning (University of Michigan) publications 1876-2013 1950-2012
University of Michigan. A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning.
523 MB
11 oversize folders
13 linear feet
976 Bimu C181 2
Publications produced by the A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning and it sub-units and architecture student organizations. Includes brochures and pamphlets, bulletins or college catalogs, directories, newsletters such as Portico, proposals, and reports. Sub-unit publications include items from the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory, the Integrated Technology Instruction Center, and the Raoul Wallenberg Lecture. Contains publications about the Art and Architecture Building including printed floor plans, proposals, and reports. Also contains student publications such as Dimensions, Rough Draft, Synergy, and the Graduation Committee publications - commencement programs and their yearbook/directory.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications were transferred from the College of Architecture + Urban Planning (Donor No. 5805 )in several accessions beginning in 1985. Publications are received on a regular basis.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Please consult the history found in the University of Michigan A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning records finding aid.
The A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture + Urban Planning Publications (11 linear feet) are divided into four series: Unit Publications; Sub-Unit Publications; Topical Publications; and Student Publications. The bulk of the publications document the College of Architecture and Urban Planning, its organization, course offerings, communications to faculty, staff, students, and alumni, and various research reports written by the college's faculty. Further research is documented in the publications of the Architectural Research Laboratory (ARL), and the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory (APRL). Some publications (or their successors) may no longer be available in print but are available on the school s website.
The 2012 accession contains digital publications donated and published by the Communications Department of the College of Architecture and Urban Planning from 2010 to 2012. Although these materials were created by a single office within the college, they correspond to three existing series within the record group: UNIT PUBLICATIONS, TOPICAL PUBLICATIONS, and STUDENT PUBLICATIONS.
The UNIT PUBLICATIONS series contains printed material published specifically by the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
The Unit Publications series (5.5 linear feet) includes articles, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins including college catalogs, directories, histories, holiday cards, lectures, manuals, newsletters, policies and procedures, posters, programs, proposals, prospectuses, and reports. The articles from Michigan Alumnus and Research News document the College of Architecture and Urban Planning from 1961 to 1988. Bulletins (college catalogs) are arranged chronologically and date as early as 1876. The print version of the bulletin is the authoritative source of admission information, course offerings and degree requirements. The college bulletins comprise almost two linear feet of the Unit Publications.
Directories such as the Faculty-Staff Directory and the Faculty Directory do not contain photographs, but do describe the faculty members' education, teaching expertise, academic and professional honors, professional experience, sponsored research, service to the community, memberships, and a select list of publications. The Bentley Historical Library holdings date from 1960 to 1999. The history More Than a Handsome Box: Education in Architecture at the University of Michigan, 1876-1986 is found in this series. The College of Architecture and Urban Planning published an internal newsletter, CAUP Newsletter, from 1987 through 1988. It was replaced in 1988 by the Newsletter. In 1999, the Newsletter was discontinued and CAUPnews, an e-mail publication represented by printouts in this record group, took its place. It was renamed TCAUP News in 2002 to reflect the name change which took place in 1999. First issued in 1984 and continuing to the present, Portico, the College's outreach publication, discusses the activities of the faculty, students, and the College's alumni and friends. This series also includes proposals and reports describing various study programs such as the Architecture Program Report dated 1986 to 1988 and the Organization of a Department of Urban Planning published in 1966. There are also reports describing Unistrut space frame systems and structural systems integrating mechanical systems.
The SUB-UNIT PUBLICATIONS series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit. The Sub-Unit Publications series (3.7 linear feet) includes publications from the Architectural Research Laboratory (ARL) and the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory.
The Architectural Research Laboratory (ARL) was founded, in 1949, by Theodore Larson, his colleagues, and students, creating the first architectural research program in the United States. The ARL publications include brochures and volumes from the ARL/UM monograph series. There are also proceedings from the Minorities in Planning and Related Professions conference as well as reports published in 1970. Also included in this series are reports on the design of Michigan and American courthouses published in the 1970s through the 1990s. Reports on child facilities will be found in the ARL subseries under Early Childhood Facilities (ECF). There are also publications from Environmental Design and Research (EDR), Man Environment Reference (MER) and School Environment Research Project (SER).
In 1974, the educational structure of the college was reorganized to create the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. To reflect this change the research mission was broadened to include the new urban planning element. The Architectural Research Laboratory became the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory (APRL). The APRL publications include brochures, manuals, and the newsletter Research News. The Bentley Library holds issues of this newsletter dating from 1984 to 1995. The bulk of publications from the APRL are reports describing energy management, manufactured housing and simulation techniques for planning and design. There are also publications from specific projects such as Design America, Factories of the Future and the Role of Design in American Corporations.
There are also publications from the Doctoral Program in Architecture, North Campus Studio and Program in Architecture (1972-1991). The Urban and Regional Planning Program (1964-2000) includes brochures, bulletins, manuals, newsletters, and proposals. This series also contains the published Raoul Wallenberg Lectures and the John Dinkeloo Lectures. They will be found in the Sub-Unit Publications series under the surnames Dinkeloo and Wallenberg.
The Topical Publications series includes printed materials published to document specific events or activities such as fund-raising or one-time conferences hosted by the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. The Topical Publications series contains publications about Alumni such as the Alumni Directory printed in 1956 and 1989, as well as information about the annual Alumni Reunion Weekend in 1990 and 1991. There is also extensive information on the Art and Architecture Building including floor plans, proposals, and reports. Researchers will also find portfolios of student work from the Design Studios of 1981 and 1994, along with abstracts of student theses from the "Thesis Final Reviews" of 2005 and 2006. There are also publications documenting the Semicentennial celebrated in 1956, and the Centennial celebrated in 2006.
The Student Publications series contains publications published by student groups within the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. The Student Publications series includes a complete run of the journal Dimensions from 1987 to the present. There are several student newsletters, including the Architectural Synthesis published from 1968 to 1969, The Allnighter, printed from 1973 to 1979, and Synergy issued from 1980 to 1983. In addition there are several other short-lived publications produced by the students.
Each year since 1980, the Graduation Committee produced a graduation yearbook containing a section for each graduating student. These individual student-designed sections frequently include a photograph and the current address of the graduating student. In some cases, however, they include designs, witticisms, invitations and notes to friends, and discussions of jobs and future plans. They are an excellent source for information not only on the graduates, but also student life in the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. The Bentley Historical Library holds these yearbooks from 1980 to 1997, and 2000.
Digital Accessions received in 20012
Materials in the Unit Publications series include brochures, newsletters, invitations, posters, and programs produced from 2010 to 2012. The brochures provide information on college admissions (as well as degree requirements, career services, student life, and facilities), fellowships and Master of Science Programs (including Conservation, Material Systems, and Digital Technologies). The college newsletter Portico, contains updates and news from the college administration and faculty as well as information on student academic honors and events. Invitations document "College on the Road" events in Chicago and receptions at the annual meetings for the American Institute of Architects and American Planning Association. Posters highlight conferences, student and faculty exhibits, and guest lectures hosted by the college, which include appearances by featured architects such as, Jeff Kipnis, Peter Eisenmen, Elizabeth Diller, and Alejandro Zaera. The programs document a luncheon honoring Taubman Scholars as well as information on modernist architects in Ann Arbor.
Programs for alumni reunion weekend events in 2010 and 2011 were added to the Topical Publications series.
Digital files added to the Student Publications series include programs for the college's annual commencement activities for 2011 and 2012, with lists of student speakers, university representatives, faculty readers, and graduates by program specialization.
Subjects:
A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Architectural Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. Architectural Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Architecture.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; Raoul Wallenberg lecture.; John Dinkeloo memorial lecture.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Architectural Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. Architectural Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Architecture.; Portico.; Dimensions.; Rough draft.
Genre/Form:
Bulletins.; Catalogs, College.; Directories.; Newsletters.; Reports.; Student publications.
- Unit Publications
  - Articles
    - Describing the College of Architecture and Urban Planning 1961-1988 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Publications of the Faculty and Students, 1976-1982, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Architecture, 1967-2000 (Box 1)
    - Architecture Program, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Art and Architecture Building, [1975] (Box 1)
    - The College of Architecture and Design, 1942-1944 (Box 1)
    - Course Descriptions--Architecture Program, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - Design Process and Methods, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Doctoral Program in Architecture, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Fine Arts at Michigan, 1950 (Box 1)
    - George Nelson--Changing the World, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Program in Architecture, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Lecture Series, 1987-1997 (Box 1)
    - Master of Urban Design Program, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Master of Urban Design Program 2001 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1968-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Urban Planning, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Admissions 2011-2012, .ZIP file
    - Fellowship Opportunities 2011, .PDF file
    - Master of Science Programs 2011, .PDF file
  - Bulletins
    - Housing Research and Education at the University of Michigan, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins (College Catalogs) arranged chronologically
    - School of Architecture Announcement, 1876 (Box 1)
    - Department of Architecture Announcement, 1910-1917 (Box 1)
    - Department of Engineering General Announcement, 1906-1911, 3 folders (Box 1)
      (includes courses in architecture)
    - Department of Engineering: General Announcement of Courses in Engineering and Architecture, 1911-1915, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Colleges of Engineering and Architecture: General Announcement of Courses, 1915-1917 (Box 1)
    - Colleges of Engineering and Architecture: General Announcement, 1917-1927, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Colleges of Engineering and Architecture Announcement, 1927-1932, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - College of Architecture Announcement, 1932-1939, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - College of Architecture and Design Announcement, 1939-1974, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - College of Architecture and Urban Planning Bulletin 1974-2000, 11 folders (Box 2)
    - A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning
      - 2002-2003 (Supplement) (Box 2)
      - General Programs and Course Descriptions
        - 2003-2004, .PDF files
        - 2004-2005, .PDF files
      - Architecture Programs and Course Descriptions
        - 2006-2007, .PDF files
        - 2008-2009, .PDF files
        - 2009-2010, .PDF files
      - Ph.D. in Urban and Regional Planning Guide 2007-2008, .PDF files
      - Urban and Regional Planning Programs and Course Descriptions
        - 2007-2008, .PDF files
        - 2008-2009, .PDF files
        - 2009-2010, .PDF files
    - College of Architecture and Design Announcement, 1947-1973, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Bulletins (College Catalog Supplements)
    - Progress Report, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
  - Calendars
    - 1986 (Box 3)
  - Directories
    - Faculty-Staff Directory, 1960-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Faculty Directory, 1990-2000, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs
    - Konrad Wachsmann: Toward Industrialization of Building, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Work, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Flyers
    - 1980-1991 undated (Box 4)
    - College of Architecture and Design Notice: Change of Entrance Requirements, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Histories
    - More than a Handsome Box: Education in Architecture at the University of Michigan, 1876-1986 by Nancy Ruth Bartlett, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Holiday Cards
    - Christmas Mailing 1989-1995, 7 folders (Box 12)
  - Indexes
    - Development Index by K. Lonberg-Holm and C. Theodore Larson, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Invitations
    - 1965-2008 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - 2010-2012, .ZIP file
      - Taubman College on the Road Event 2010
      - Michigan Reception, AIA Conference 2012
      - University Alumni Reception, APA Conference 2012
  - Journals
    - Central, 1980-1983, 1986, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Lectures
    - Growing a Vision by James Polshek and Douglas Kelbaugh (Box 4)
  - Manuals
    - Architecture Program Student Handbook, 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - New Student Handbook 1990-1993, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Newsletters
    - CAUP Newsletter, 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 4)
      (see also Newsletter, 1988-1999)
    - CAUPnews (e-mail printout), 1999-2001, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Network News, 1992-1994, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - News From Taubman College, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter, 1988-1999, 11 folders (Box 4)
      (see also CAUP Newsletter, 1987-1988)
    - Portico, 1984-2009
      - 1984-2005, 12 folders (Box 4)
      - 2006-2009, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Portico, 2010-2011, .ZIP file
    - TCAUP News (e-mail printout), 2002-2004 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Urban Network News, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Youth & Advocacy, 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Policies and Procedures
    - College Rules
      - 1986-1994 (scattered) (Box 5)
      - 1996 (Box 5)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 5)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 5)
      - 2001 (Box 5)
      - 2002 (Box 5)
    - Rules of the College of Architecture and Urban Planning, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Research Policies and Procedures 1993-1994 (Box 12)
  - Posters
    - Lecture Posters, 1975-1978, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Admissions, undated (Folder 1)
    - Conferences 2007, 2010-2012 (Folder 2)
    - Construction Lecture Series, Winter 2012 (Folder 3)
    - Discipline Lecture Series, Winter 2011 (Folder 4)
    - Fall/Winter Events, 1986-1999 (scattered) (Folder 5)
    - Fall/Winter Events, 2000-2007 (Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Exhibit, 2010-2011 (Folder 8)
    - Representation Lecture Series, Fall 2011 (Folder 9)
    - Technique Lecture Series, Fall 2010 (Folder 10)
    - Studio Review & Thesis Review, 2010-2012 (Folder 11)
    - 2010-2011, .ZIP file
      - Advancing Architectural Praxis Symposium
      - Fall Lecture Series
      - Future of Technology Conference
      - Robert C. Metcalf Exhibit
      - Fellows Exhibit
      - Fresh Student Exhibition
      - Future of History Conference
      - Modernism at Risk Exhibit
      - Research Through Making Exhibition
      - Thesis Exhibit
      - Wallenberg Competition Studio Symposium
      - Winter Lecture Series
    - 2011-2012, .ZIP file
      - Curating Race, Curating Space Conference
      - Fall Lecture Series
      - Framing a Cultural Ideal Symposium
      - Power Conference
      - Research Through Making Exhibition
      - Risk Conference
      - Scenes From Studio Student Exhibition
      - Thesis Exhibit
      - Wallenberg Competition Studio Symposium
      - Whither Installation Symposium
      - Winter Lecture Series
  - Press Release
    - 1998 (Box 5)
  - Programs
    - Celebration and Naming Ceremony, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Culture and the Environment: An Urban Education Conference, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1988-1997 (Box 5)
    - New Schools for New Education: An Architectural Workshop Conducted by the Department of Architecture in Collaboration with the School of Education, University of Michigan, on Behalf of Educational Facilities Laboratories Inc. (Ford Foundation), 1959 (Box 5)
    - "The Place of Work" -- student exhibition undated (Box 12)
    - Scholarship and Patronage Celebration October 2005 (Box 12)
    - A2Modern: Selected Works of Residential Modern Architects and Map, 2012, .ZIP file
    - Taubman Scholars Luncheon, 2010, .ZIP file
  - Proposals
    - A Proposal to the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies for a Certification in Gaming/Simulation Studies
      - April 1985 (Box 5)
      - October 1985 (Box 5)
  - Prospectus
    - College of Architecture + Urban Planning: Defining Our Future, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Reports
    - Architecture Program Report, 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Educational Development Plan, 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Housing Needs for the Elderly: A Quantitative Analysis by Benjamin Handler, circa 1982 (Box 5)
    - Housing Research and Education, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Architecture Papers
      - The Work of TEN Arquitectos by Enrique Norten, no. 3, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Organization of a Department of Urban Planning: The U. of M., 1966 (Box 5)
    - Prototype Structural System Integrating Mechanical Services, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Town/Gown Study, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Unistrut Space-Frame System, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Environmental Change: A Case Study of Office Relocation at the University of Michigan December 1991 (Box 12)
    - Report on Scholarly and Research Activity 1996-1997 (Box 12)
    - Research Activities 1994-1995 (brief summaries of research projects) (Box 12)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  - Ann Arbor Conference
    - Proceedings (Box 6)
      - Papers Presented at the Seventh Ann Arbor Conference: Mid-Century Report on Design Progress, Review-Preview, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Architectural Research Laboratory
    - Unit Publications
      - Brochures
        - Miscellaneous undated (Box 6)
        - Unistrut System of Construction, 1950 (Box 6)
      - Catalogs
        - Publications of the Architectural Research Laboratory, 1972-1980, 1980 (Box 6)
      - Monograph Series
        - Assessing Housing Preferences of Low Cost Single Family Home Buyers, by Robert E. Johnson, 1980 (Box 6)
        - Life Imitates Architecture: Taliesin and Alden Dow's Studio, by Sidney K. Robinson, 1980 (Box 6)
        - Comprehensive Planning for Housing in Developing Countries, by Samir El Sadek, 1980 (Box 6)
        - Computer Modeling in Hospital Planning: Three Case Studies, by Frank Zilm, 1980 (Box 6)
      - Proceedings
        - Minorities in Planning and Related Urban Professions, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Reports
        - The American Courthouse: Planning and Design for the Judicial Process, 1993 (Box 6)
        - The American Courthouse: A Planning and Design Guide for Its Future Development, volume 2, 1971 (Box 6)
        - HUD-Supported Work-Study Projects for Minorities in Planning and Related Professions, August 1970 (Box 6)
        - The Michigan Courthouse Study: Statistical Summary and Design Guidelines, volume 1, 1981 (Box 6)
        - Minorities in Planning and Related Urban Professions, February 1970 (Box 6)
        - Minorities in Planning and Related Urban Professions: The Planning Agencies View of the Program: Summary of Agency Questionnaire Responses, January 1970 (Box 6)
        - The Physical Environment and the Learning Process: A Survey of Recent Research by Jonathan King and Robert W. Marans, 1979 (Box 6)
        - Pilot Study for an Evaluation of the Effectiveness of Infrared Scanning as a Tool for Measuring the Thermal Performance of Buildings, 1976 (Box 6)
        - Pre-Construction Evaluation: A Report on the Full Scale Mock-Up and Evaluation of Hospital Rooms by Jonathan King, Robert W. Marans and Lois Ann Solomon, 1982 (Box 6)
        - The Regional Housing Centre Bandung, Indonesia by C. Theodore Larson and Stephen C.A. Paraskevopoulos, 1958 (Box 6)
        - Research on Potential of Advanced Technology for Housing: A Building System Based on Filament Winding and New Developments in Water and Waste Management, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Sub-Unit Publications
      - Agency for International Development (Box 7)
        - Reports
          - The Potential Use of Foam Plastics for Housing in Underdeveloped Areas, 1963 (Box 7)
          - Structural Potential of Foam Plastics for Housing in Underdeveloped Areas, 1966 (Box 7)
      - Bureau of Facilities
        - Reports
          - State Computer Based Building Information System, 1974 (Box 7)
      - Early Childhood Facilities
        - Reports
          - An Annotated Bibliography on Early Childhood, 1970 (Box 7)
          - Some European Nursery Schools and Playgrounds, 1970 (Box 7)